Today I am going to present a very
general summary of the history of humanity.
I will be using the latest version of our
world history timeline,
which is available as a poster on
our website usefulcharts.com.   I'm going to
show you how
history can be divided into several
periods or ages and explain how these
divisions help to highlight some of
the most important turning points
in world history.
[music]
Let me start by briefly explaining
how this chart works.  The
vertical axis represents the passage of time,
which advances as we go further
down.  Each white line represents 100
years and the scale is equidistant,
meaning that the distance between any two
lines at the top of the chart is
exactly the same as if we were at
the base.  This is important
because it allows us to make
accurate comparisons, as well as giving the viewer
an appropriate perspective of time.
Horizontally, the different sections
of the chart represent different
parts of the world.  So, on the
far left we can see all of
America, the Middle East, Asia and
finally the Pacific islands.
Each line in the graph represents a
specific culture, civilization, or empire.  And how wide each
line is represents the relative importance
of that culture when compared
to others from the same period or region.
Okay, now that we've cleared all that up,
the next question we need to
answer is, when does the
story begin?  In other words, where do we
draw the line between history and
prehistory?
Well, in this chart we use the year
3300 BC as a
starting point.  The reason for choosing this year
is that it was around this time that
writing first appeared.  The basic idea is that without
written records we cannot have
history.  Therefore, everything
prior to the emergence of the first
writing systems is categorized as
prehistory.
Of course, prehistory extends
much further back in time, much more
than 5300 years.  If we talk about the
prehistory of our species, Homo
sapiens, it extends another 200,000 years.
a period also known as the
Stone Age.  And if we're talking about the
prehistory of planet Earth, in that
case, prehistory extends 4.5
billion years, but this chart
simply doesn't include prehistory.
Instead, it begins with the emergence
of written documents and starts from
that point.
So in this chart, history is
divided into six main periods: the
early Bronze Age, the
Bronze Age, the Iron Age,
Classical Antiquity, the Middle Ages, and the
Modern Age.  Let's take a look at each
one.
The Bronze Age gets its name from the
fact that humans began
making things out of bronze around
the same time they
first developed writing.  This occurred
in three main areas.
Egypt,
Sumeria, what would be present-day Iraq, and
the Indus Valley, roughly
present-day Pakistan.
Unfortunately,
the writing system used in the
Indus Valley has not yet been deciphered, so we can only
read the records provided by Egypt and
Sumeria.
But what we do know is that these three
civilizations traded with each other and
that throughout the Bronze Age
each one grew in size and
technological development.
At the beginning of this period, the
Sumerians had already invented the wheel,
the plow, and the sail.
But during the early Bronze Age
they would manage to develop astronomy and
mathematics.
In Egypt, it was during the early
Bronze Age that the great pyramids of
Guisas were built.
Besides these three civilizations, the
only other place in the world where
we find large cities is in what
is now Peru.
There, a civilization known as
Caral Supe was flourishing,
but strangely, although they built
large stone structures, they seem to have had
neither a writing system
nor pottery.
We can also find
stone structures dating from the early
Bronze Age at Stonehenge in England and on
the island of Malta.
But none of these places had
large populations.
Okay, that would be the early
Bronze Age.  Now let's turn our attention
to the Bronze Age proper.
What divides these two periods is a
very important event known as the
4.2 kiloyear event,
so named because it occurred
approximately 4.2 thousand years ago.  The
exact cause of the event is still debated,
but what we do know is that it caused
around 100 years of
extremely dry conditions worldwide.
For this reason, the Old Kingdom of
Egypt, the Akkadian Empire, which had
conquered Sumeria, and the
Indus Valley Civilization all began to
deteriorate rapidly, and in the period
that follows we see a new group of
cultures.
Egypt recovered under the Middle
and New Kingdoms, and the Sumerian civilization
eventually evolved into the
Babylonian civilization.
But in South Asia we can see an
even more drastic change.
The cities of the Indus Valley
simply disappear and we see a
new people arrive, the Indo-Aryans,
who were part of the
Indo-European group.
During the Bronze Age
proper, we also see
civilizations emerge in other parts of the world
for the first time, including in China,
sub-Saharan Africa, and, though
unknown to many, North America.
There we find the Poverty
Point culture, where large
mounds and complex settlements were built.
Finally, we also get the first
civilization in Europe, the Minoans, on
the island of Crete.  In the middle of this
age, a volcanic eruption occurred nearby,
leading to the fall of the
Minoans and the rise of the
Menian Greeks.
This catastrophe was most
likely the event that gave birth to the
myth of Atlantis.
The next turning point occurred
around 1200 BC and this
is known as the Bronze Age collapse
.
For reasons that are still not very clear,
the major civilizations in
Greece, Anatolia, and Egypt
all disappeared almost instantly.
What followed is often called the
Greek Dark Ages, a period in which
we observe a remarkable absence of
historical records.
Interestingly, it is during this
dark period that
many of the world's most famous
legendary tales supposedly took place, such as those
found in the Jewish Torah, the
Greek Iliad, and the
Hindu Mahabharata.
The collapse of the Bronze Age also
coincided with the first use of iron
in the Middle East.  Therefore, the
time period in which the
Greek Dark Ages took place is also known
as the Iron Age.
This is the third and final period in
what is known as the three-
age system, consisting of the Stone Age,
the Bronze Age, and the Iron Age.
The following period is not actually
part of the three-age system.
This is because from
approximately 600 BC onwards we do not have to
rely entirely on
archaeology for information.
As I mentioned earlier, humans
have been writing since 3300
BC, but there is nothing that
survives from the Bronze or
Iron Ages that can be considered a
history book.
We certainly have lists of kings, lists of
battles, and other details engraved in
stone and metal, but we have nothing
that begins with "In this treatise I will
record the complete history of X."
However, in this era we do begin
to find this type of writing, for
example, by a Greek man
named Herodotus, who is
often referred to as the father of
history.
So, in other words, we know
much more about the next period
called classical antiquity than we do
about earlier periods.
Classical antiquity is when the
Greeks and Romans laid the foundations
for what would become known as
Western civilization, mainly by
taking elements and building upon
information gained from earlier
Bronze Age civilizations.
But there were also many things
happening in other parts of the world.
For example, in Mesoamerica, the
Olmec culture would contribute its influence to the
later Classic Mayan culture with its
complex calendar and
writing system.  And in North America there was an
extensive trade network where many
different types of art were
exchanged.
In Africa, the long-lasting kingdom of Kush
eventually gave way to the Imperioite in
Ethiopia.   There
were also the three powerful
Persian empires, the Mauryan and
Gupta empires in India, and the first
imperial dynasty in China.  Over time,
a trade route opened up between all
these areas, known as the
Silk Road, and the western
and eastern parts of Eurasia were
connected for the first time.  But perhaps
even more important is that during
classical antiquity the
current philosophical and moral foundations of
humanity were laid.
Simultaneously, though independently,
Greek philosophy, the Bible,
Buddhist and Hindu scriptures, and the writings of
confusion emerged.   We
also see the first experiments
with democracy and the first evidence
of true scientific thinking.
But this golden age of
human development did not last forever.  It came to an
end around the year 500 AD
with the fall of the Western Roman Empire
.
In other regions, the classical period
ended a little earlier, as in China, or a
little later, as in Mesoamerica,
but basically all over the world,
most of the major
classical civilizations eventually
came to an end.
It is then that we arrive at what is
called the Middle Ages.  The word "middle"
is used for this period, as it is
located in the middle between
ancient history, which consists of everything we
have seen so far, and
modern history, which we will see shortly.  It is also
called the medieval period, because
medieval simply means the
Middle Ages.
But one term we really
shouldn't use to refer to
this whole period, although it is often used,
is the dark ages.  The reason is that
the so-called dark ages are really
limited only to Western Europe.
Other areas during this time, such as the
Middle East and China, were indeed
experiencing new golden ages.
So what caused things
to change so drastically in
Western Europe?
Well, several theories were proposed,
but one thing we know for sure is that it
involved large migrations in
various parts of the world.  Whether
or not these migrations were motivated
by climate change or some other
natural event is something we cannot
say for sure,
but it ended up creating a certain kind of
domino effect.  For example, some
migrated to Europe from the east, and this
pushed several Germanic tribes further
south, leading to conflict with Rome.
Over time, it was these
Germanic tribes, known to the Romans
as the barbarians, who caused the
fall of the Western Roman Empire and
plunged Europe into the so-called
Dark Ages.
But it wasn't only the barbarians
who caused problems.  In the years
535 and 536
there were extreme weather events,
perhaps caused by a large
volcanic eruption, which led to famines and
cold, dry climates around the world.
The first bubonic plague also occurred
, known as the Plague of
Justinian, which killed 50% of the
population in some cities.
In the east, these events did not lead
to the fall of the eastern part of the
empire, but they did pave the way
for the emergence of a new civilization
very close by, Islam.
But while Islam was expanding in the
Middle East, Christianity was
expanding in Europe.  Over time,
regions that began as
barbarian kingdoms would develop into
great powers such as England,
France, and the Holy Roman Empire
.
But there were also many other things
happening in the world during the
Middle Ages.  For example, in West Africa
we see the emergence of several great
empires for the first time, such as
the Mali Empire with its leader
Mansamusa, who was the richest person
in all of world history.  And in southern
Africa there was the city of Great
Zimbabwe, which included the first
great structures in the history of
that part of the world.  A lot of things
were also happening in America.
We are not used to thinking about the
existence of cities in
pre-Columbian North America, but this was
a reality.  There were Kahoquia in
present-day Illinois, as well as the
Anasasi cities in New
Mexico.
In Mesoamerica, the Aztecs dominated, and
in South America there were the Incas.
Finally, it was during the Middle Ages
that we see the birth of the largest land empire
of all time, the
Mongol Empire started by Heniscan.
Okay, we have now reached the sixth and
final period, the modern age, which
is the period in which we live today.  One
could argue that the transition
began with the deadliest pandemic of
all time, the Black Death,
also known as the second
bubonic plague.
Once again, up to 50% of the
population in many cities died, and
this perhaps helped to fuel the
renaissance.
The Eastern Roman Empire finally
fell to the Ottoman Turks, and in
Italy there was a renewed interest in
studying the art and philosophy of the
classical period.   At about the
same time,
Europeans began to colonize America
and great advances were made in
science.
This in turn led to the
industrial revolution, which at the same time
paved the way for the
scientific revolution that we continue to experience
today.
Okay, that was obviously a very
general summary,
but I think perhaps the most interesting
and important thing is the similarities that
can be seen in the transitions between
each period.  It often involves a
combination of climate events,
mass migrations, and pandemics—three
things we are living with in
this decade.  This means that we are about to
enter a new period in
the history of humanity.
I guess only time will tell.
Let me know what you think in the
comments.  Thanks for watching.